Hello, everyone. Welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford. And I am John Petrella. And the purpose of this program is to give Medford citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices and to discover city services or businesses you may not have been aware of.
And our guest today, and I know a lot of people know him, is Chris Suma of the Method Health Department. Welcome, Chris. It is great to have you on the show. I appreciate that. Thank you for having me. And we're going to get right into it. Beautiful.
Why don't you tell our listeners who is Chris Zuma, your background. We'll start that way. You mean aside from the international man of mystery? There you go. Aside from that. That's why I said everyone knows you.
So, I am a recovery coach. I'm a recovery coach with North Suffolk Community Services. I'm also the recovery coach for the City of Medford. And I also work with the Board of Health for Medford, the Office of Outreach and Prevention, Medford Police doing follow-up door knocks. So, like if someone overdoses, we go and offer them services. So, stuff like that. I'm a community guy. I'm in the community a lot.
But a little bit about my background. So I'm just, I'm an ordinary guy. I like to think that I'm a guy that has been to the depths of darkness and has found the way to bathe in the light, if that makes sense. Makes sense. Yeah.
Had you know, I regular upbringing grew up in in Winthrop And for me substances came in when I was in eighth grade It was peer pressure to drink and I wanted to fit in with the older kids and stuff like that it's it's a common story that a lot of a lot of guys excuse me a lot of kids deal with yep, and That led to drink in and then it led to marijuana and then you know, I dealt with
something personal, it was an assault that happened, and then I started, I found opiates, and then once the opiates came into the picture, it was, you know, that was kind of where everything focused. Did that for a long time, and the natural progression with opiates, you know, the regular perks into the more stronger ones, and so on and so forth. And I got through school, you know, I was still using, I was always an athlete, played sports my whole life.
got recruited to play baseball went to college and played baseball in college and then someone introduced me to oxycontin and that's kind of when everything went downhill um once oxycontin came into the picture everything went downhill um i ended up i stopped using oxycontin because
too much information but they made it where it would turn into a gel when you crushed it or whatever you're doing and if water hit it and I stopped and here I am thinking you know what am I gonna do for work because I'm I don't have a job I'm living at home at this point like I had been stealing from family and yeah you name it it came with the turf right and um
I had worked jobs as like a bouncer, you know, working at nightclubs and bars and stuff like that. So here I am thinking, all right, it was a phase I went through. What skills do I have that I can get a job? And it just made sense at the time. Well, you've been a bouncer for so long, be a bouncer of the street. So I joined the police department and I worked in Boston for like 12 years. And I'd like to say that I did the right thing those whole 12 years. Yeah, but I did not.
And it progressed from the Oxycontin, then it was the Perc 30s, then it was Heroin, then it was Fentanyl. And I sustained the job for a while, and then eventually, you know, I could do it until I couldn't do it anymore. And once that happened, it was a great thing that happened. I mean, I didn't get in trouble or anything. I didn't kill anybody, more importantly. That's what's most important. And then, you know, I ended up
sinking into a depression after a couple of failed suicide attempts I ended up
I woke up after the last one, and I had a conversation with my mother, and for whatever reason, that conversation, she just said to me, like, what are you doing? There's no rhyme or reason to this. Why are you doing this? And for whatever reason, in that conversation, when I looked in her eyes, I saw every time that I pawned her wedding ring, every time that I stole, every time that I ran up, credit card debt, or whatever it was, and I said, all right, I'm done.
And I detoxed cold turkey off of fentanyl in my parents' attic. It took me like over a week, like two weeks to get the sick feeling out of me. But then I thought, all right, I'm through it, I'm okay. That went on for two years. And what's crazy about those two years is in those two years, I was living the life of an addict that just wasn't using.
I was depressed, I was obsessed over my drug, I was suicidal, I was... you name it. And nothing good. So it's all still there, you're just not doing the drugs. Exactly. All of the behaviors are the same. It's just the substances were removed.
So I mean like I was living in filth. You know yeah, it was terrible yeah, and Somebody said to me like did you ever try meetings, and I said it's not for me You know I don't do that like those aren't my people you know I can't get involved with that And I'll never forget the guy said to me if those aren't your people then they're exactly where you need to be And I said what do you mean, and he said to me well your people helped land you here. Maybe it's time to
pick a different set of people. There you go. So I walked into a meeting, first meeting I ever went to was the Looney Nooney at Club 24 in Malden. It's an AA meeting and I was a predominantly drug guy. Right, yeah. I raised my hand, I poured it all out and I left there with a sponsor, I left there with phone numbers and it's been
you know, pedal to the metal since then. Just work and recovery and just being a regular guy. And now, you know, like everything comes back. A lot of people, you know, they say like, Oh, I want the car, I want the house, you know, blah, blah, blah, all the material things. And all of that stuff comes back. But
To be totally honest with you, I would set fire to all of that if it meant that I missed out on one minute of that connection with my family, being present. Today, I'm a good family man. I'm the rock of my family today, and I used to be the drain on my family. So, you know, I'm just a guy who just wants to pass off what I have to other people to help them see that side of me. You ran the whole gamut, Chris. That's what you did.
You know, it's a sad story in a way, but it's also a great story because You know you went through it all and now you're a recovery coach. I mean, so that's It's wonderful how it ended up. I'm happy it ended up that way believe me true because a lot of times it doesn't I don't have to tell you All right, so
You know, the Method Health Department, you know, responsible for several areas. Can you, I mean, you gave us some of it. Can you describe your role with the, you know, with the Office of Prevention and Outreach? That's what it's considered, right? Office of Prevention.
Yes. What's your role? So my role with the Office of Outreach and Prevention is I'm the substance guy. So anybody that comes in or anybody that's looking for help with substances, if they're addicted, if they're teetering on addiction, anybody that's dealing with any substances, I'm the guy that will meet you, talk to you. I run groups out of the city of Medford. There's a group on Wednesdays that I run.
It's 430 to 530 at City Hall, and that's an all-recovery group. Everybody's welcome, doesn't matter where you're at in recovery, and it's a support group. So I run it a little different than other groups, like we support each other, and also we provide food, so you get pizza, salad, chicken fingers, it's nice. I gotta come up there some day. I'd love to have you.
And I also, which is near and dear to my heart, I get to run a first responder and veterans group, which is fantastic. It's real near and dear to my heart. It's Tuesday nights at First Baptist Church, seven o'clock in Medford. And it's great because it's a safe place for people that have seen what we've seen, done what we've done, to come and have a safe outlet to talk about stuff.
So I try to get involved in as many events as I possibly can and just be out in the community meeting the public and just offering assistance any way I can. Yeah and you are out in the community because a lot of people know you. I mentioned your name people know you and that's a good thing. It is. Yeah it really is. All right so I always hear Method Connects
community engagement team what is it that they do what what do they do so in short the uh... the engagement team uh... it it links people upward services and resources and it might be people that might normally not
be aware of the resources and stuff. So like, we're out in the community, we're out there, you know, making people aware that like, you know, we have a social service coordinator, which you've interviewed, we have, you know, a person that deals with the youth, we have a person that deals with the seniors. I mean, it runs the gambit of like everything you could potentially need. And it's just, it's just helping people be aware of what, you know, they could potentially get from the city to help them with whatever challenges they're dealing with.
And there's a lot of challenges out there. And there is a lot of different groups. Oh yeah. You just said it. Oh yeah. Children, adults, veterans, I mean. Absolutely. This past year, I believe we've serviced like 8,000 people. Wow. Yeah. It's fantastic. You know, like it really is. That's incredible. It's amazing. Just being out there in the community and like going to the different events, you'd be surprised how many people you actually come in contact with. What do you do? And it's, oh yeah, oh yeah, well let me put you in touch with this one. Let me put you in touch with this one.
And that's how it goes, and it's a beautiful thing. And you have a good idea. Well, you don't have a good idea. You put them in touch.
You know, I guess I'm gonna say it like this, you get them to the right people. Absolutely. Basically. I always like to say, if I don't have the answers that you're looking for, I will put you in touch with someone that does have the right answers. Yeah. Because under no circumstances do I act like I know it all, because I don't. But I can put you in touch with the right people. Okay. And that's key. Yeah. It always is. Yeah.
When you're first trying to get off and, you know, meet the people that handled you at the beginning. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Very important. All right. So can you tell us when, where, what takes place? That's a loaded question. Sure.
uh... you know at one of the meetings sure you know uh... so the the wednesday all recovery group like i said from four thirty to five thirty at city hall uh... food is provided pizza salad chicken fingers and it's a different approach to your standard a a n n a meetings uh... the majority of people seem to go to one or the other there's a ton of meetings and i'm open to any meeting okay uh...
But my approach is a little different because some people are intimidated, excuse me, by like the 12 steps and stuff like that. So I don't push any of that stuff. This is just a safe place where people can come in wherever you are in your recovery and you can just dump onto the table how you're feeling and get positive constructive feedback from other like-minded people.
that are trying to be the best version of themselves. And in those meetings a lot of times someone, like I try to have everybody share in the room and someone will share something and then for that minute like I'll turn to them and it'll almost be kind of like a one-on-one where it's like no one else is in the room except us and we're having a conversation and we're just talking. I'm not telling people what to do, we're just discussing
you know, pros, cons, how they feel about it. Ultimately, it's whatever they want to do with their life, their recovery. It's just good to have something to bounce, someone to bounce it off of who has been in your shoes and has found the way out, because that way we can avoid a lot of the pitfalls that we fall into in recovery if you're talking to other people that have already found that path and walked out. You know, we have the blueprint, so.
We give it away freely, it's just a matter of if you're willing to try it. Now, you know, this is kind of a part of this, but, you know, when you, I know different people come and go and all that. When you do these meetings, right, so if someone just walks in off the street, I mean,
What happens, I mean I walk in off the street, I'm a mess Chris. I mean there's other people there. I mean is it tough for someone to just come in there and, I mean how do you, I mean. So a lot of times what I do is I try to bring in humor.
uh... so like this is a joke and and i well i i have to be honest at my meetings i'd talk a lot more crass i'd talk a lot more of course yep because you know what i'm i'm relating to the people that are there that's that's what i'm there to get up and i always say that like that joke in and that
personality and connection cracks the door open so recovery can kick it in. You know what I mean? So it's getting comfortable. So like normally when someone walks in, they sit down and I greet right away, you know, hey, how you doing, blah, blah, blah. But then once the meeting starts, it's a joke with people in the meeting, but I loudly say, and who are you? And the reason why I do that is because they crack a smile and then it makes them uncomfortable.
Because this whole recovery thing is about getting comfortable being uncomfortable. So I want you to get uncomfortable in the group. That's when we grow. We don't grow in comfort. Comfort zone is where dreams go to die. We can't do that. I love that. We can't do that. So it's like you're going to come, you might be a little uncomfortable, but it's all love, all support, all the time.
and you get them out of the comfort zone, so to speak. Absolutely. And what's great about the group, too, is like people, they celebrate different lengths of clean time, sobriety, whatever you want to call it. And a lot of times when someone celebrates, we'll go to a meeting and like six, seven, eight of us will go just to support. It doesn't matter if it's one month, two months, a year, two years, it doesn't matter. We all just support.
So you know I always, you know I had growing up friends whatever but some of them it seems like, I mean they're,
did everything right, you know, they went into programs, came out. I gotta say, a lot of them stayed away from the people they used to hang around with. You never saw them in a bar again, stuff like that. So, is it different for everybody? I mean, is it always you're in recovery? Some people, I mean, does it take,
You know, I'm looking at like the time difference. Some people it takes long, short. I mean, how do you, it's gotta be like, a hell of a lot of work. It's confusing. To say the least. Yeah, no, I mean, how do you? I'll tell you, there's no one path to recovery. Everybody's recovery is their own. For me, I can only speak from my point of view.
Um, I just stopped associating with it. There's an old saying that if you hang around a barber shop long enough, you're going to get a haircut and it's true. So if I'm around drugs and alcohol on a regular basis, I look at it like the clock is ticking. Why am I going to do that? You know, like I spent so long in the dock that now that I'm in the light, if anybody's going to try to pull me in the shade, sorry.
You're not people that I'm associating with. It's not going to happen. It ain't happening. And one of the biggest things that I push is show me the five people you hang out with, they'll show you exactly who you are or where you're going. And I wish that I learned that at a younger age, but it's true. You know, like if you're hanging out with people that their idea of a weekend is getting blasted and doing something stupid,
chances are you might fall into that. But if you're hanging around with people that are at home with their families, buying houses, living lives, being the best version of themselves, chances are you're gonna rise to the level that you set around you. You know what I mean? So it's tough though, because- I'm sure it is. We have people go out, we have people come back in, go out, come in, go out, come in. And unfortunately, there's a lot of loss that comes with this job. And the losses outweigh the victories by a lot.
Yeah. But those victories, that's someone's life. That's someone's father, someone's brother, someone's son. It's, you know, when you see that light come back on in someone and, like, they're hungry for it and they're willing to do what they have to do to get it, it's moving. It's incredible. It is. It's a beautiful thing. A beautiful thing. Unfortunately, I've seen both sides of that. I know exactly what you're talking about. I had some good friends and, you know, we grew up in a different time.
It was, there was a lot of junk around and you know, too easy to get at and everything else and it's, yeah. I had friends that I used to use with and then I got my stuff together, they got their stuff together and then we reconnected and go to find out, oh well I drink all the time. And it was a happy moment because I got my friend back.
But it was also a sad moment because I realized you're not my crew anymore And we still text but like we haven't seen each other since because that's not what I choose to spend my day doing Yeah, I'm all about improving in all ways. You know, I'm always improving in all ways mentally emotionally physically spiritually That's what you gotta do. Yeah. Yeah All right, so, you know
If you had to give someone advice to anyone, you know, someone's looking to get into a recovery program, I mean, I wouldn't even know what to begin with, but what advice do you give them? I mean, do it.
And I know that sounds ridiculous. No, it really doesn't. So there's a lot of fear around getting into it. And what I've learned is the greatest way to deal with fear or anxiety is to just do it scared. I mean, deep down, we know what we have to do. You know, walk into a meeting, raise your hand, talk about what's going on. You'll be surprised the amount of support that you get from people you don't know.
talk to professionals, come and talk to me, come and talk to anybody that's in this field can direct you on what might be a good fit for you. And it's just a matter of taking that first step. I always say that
Sloppy action beats perfect planning every single time, because you can refine the sloppy action. But when you're focused on, I have to have a perfect plan on how I'm going to get my life back, and this, that, and the other thing, you never end up taking that first step. Just start. Just take that first step, walk in and say, I'm Chris, or whoever, whatever your name is, and I need help.
It makes sense. You simplify it, but it does make sense. I hear that loud and clear. So, I know you guys, it's a big operation. There's a lot that goes on. I mean, you know, we've had a few other guests on, as you know. And I tell you, the shows did great. People were interested, and I think a lot of people have
You know, no idea what's really going on out there. And it does. It's going on. You guys are doing incredible work. Appreciate that. No, you are. I mean, there's no two ways about it. So, you know, as someone who does this, you know, for a living, and you've been through everything, you know, what's your biggest, you know, what's your biggest challenge for what you do? You know, like, how do you, like, there's gotta be things that happen.
that got a uh... you know i don't wanna say tear your heart out but boy there's gotta be some tough situations you're in challenges that you gotta go through i mean how do you deal with with with issues i mean and i'm not just talking to people i'm talking you know the financial end of it everything there's so much involved unfortunately uh... i feel like it's getting better yeah i think that the stigma around this
holds a lot of people back. And it's sad because so much is happening now and there's so much more put into mental health, there's so much more put into recovery and addiction, substance use disorder, that
That stigma is something that will prevent a lot of people from speaking up. It'll prevent a lot of people from taking a first step. It'll prevent, depending on what your job is, you don't want to be seen in that light, and I can relate to that. The way that I combat that is I try to lead by example. I try to put myself out there as much as I possibly can, open book, talk about everything that's going on, everything that I do, everything, and show that
we do get better. You know, we, even though, you know, we've, we've sank down to really low depths, it doesn't mean that we're just, you know, we should be discarded. Right. It's just a matter of just
putting yourself out there. This is me. Love me or hate me. This is me. And that's, you know, I tell everybody that I work with, you know, you have to work on your inner peace. Forget about what other people think. Work on how you feel about you and what's coming from inside. And if you can get to a place where you're carrying around joy and happiness and love and serenity and peace,
The outside world it doesn't matter as much what people are thinking, you know what I mean? It's about how you feel about you Can you look yourself in the mirror at night when no one else is around and be happy with the person looking back at you? And then just take the steps take the steps. Yeah, that's what you got to do. It's a big thing. Yeah, it makes sense to absolutely. Yeah I
I know there's a lot going on right now. You know, I see all these, I wouldn't call them advertisements, but you're putting it out there. They had the, was it the flags? And they had all kinds of stuff. Adopt-A-Pole was another one. That was a beautiful thing too. It was great. This was the first year that Medford took part in it. Yeah, I think it was awesome. It was fantastic. Yeah, fantastic.
I mean, you guys did a lot lot to get that that accomplished. Yep. So do you have any other like special events or things that you might want people to know about that are coming up or yeah, so the next big one that's coming up is Medford. We're doing a recovery fest. Okay, yep, it's going to be September 12 at the Condon shell.
from one to three. Oh really? Anybody's welcome to come. Okay. There's going to be refreshments, there's going to be like games, there's going to be resource tables set up. I think as of right now we have over 20 resource tables that are coming to set up. Nice. And it's just different ways that you can find out a way that you might be able to get assistance, you might be able to get help.
and just have a good time. You come down for the fun, you come down for the fellowship, come down for the food. And it's just a matter of just networking and making good connections with quality people that can potentially assist you in your journey. So yeah, it's gonna be a good time. We're gonna have speakers, we're gonna have performers. Yeah, it's gonna be good. So at this stage of my life, I'm coming for the food, is that okay? I would hope so. Let's be real. Why do you think I'm going down for the food?
I'm telling you So probably you know last question. I really haven't and I want to just say this great everything I think people really do learn a lot when we do these type of shows I I think we like people get a better understanding what it's all about and
And I can't say it enough. You guys really do. It's important. And not only is it important you guys do a good job, you really do. I wish you guys were around, oh, I don't know, 30 years ago, maybe? 40? Oh, actually, about 50 years ago. You're dating yourself. Yeah, I know, but who am I kidding? Who am I kidding? Really, it's great what you do. Thank you.
can you give us, I mean, someone wants to reach you, okay, what's the easiest way to
Websites, phone numbers, what can you give us, let people know how to reach you? Or the office, whatever it is. If you want to look at the website through the office, it's just on the MedFed website. It's under the Office of Outreach and Prevention. You can find me there. But the easiest way to get in touch with me is you can just email or call me direct. My email is csumma, that's c-s-u-m-m-a, at medfed-ma.gov.
Or you can reach me on my cell phone at 617-293-0008. Or you can come in on Wednesday nights to the all recovery meeting if you want to pop in there. If you're a first responder or a veteran you can come in on Tuesday nights. And that's from what? 205 or is that what it is? 210. 210. Is it 210? 210 or 205? It's on the second floor. We know it's on the second floor.
I should have these answers. Well, no, no, that's all right, because I probably, I don't know, I always thought it was either 205, but maybe it is 210. What do I know? For some reason, I think 210 is my office there. So you know what, though? It's on the second floor right next to the mayor's office. So people know how to get there. That's all. I'm going to ask you one more time.
Give us that information again, how to reach you. So the best way to reach me is through email at csuma at medfed-ma.gov or on my cell phone 617-293-0008 or you can just come like I said to the meetings and drop in and you know we can talk there and get you set up or what you need and we start this journey.
And it's a good journey. It's a fantastic journey. It's not easy. It's simple just don't use but it's not easy, but we get there together It's a tough journey, but yeah, we get there together and that's the beauty of this like you're not alone The most important thing like when people start working with me is you're not alone You know like other people have done this other people are dealing with this. Yeah, because because in the beginning you feel
No one understands me, I'm by myself. Right, that's true, that's a good point. And that's not it. There are people that understand you, there are people that care, there are people that will support. Always. Surround yourself with those people and the sky's the limit.
You know, it's that time again. I could talk to you for, you know, a couple of hours. Maybe someday we'll do that. But it is that time again. I want to thank you, Chris, from the Method Health Department, for joining us. I want to wish you
and the Method Health Department continued success. And I mean that. You guys do a great job, something the city, really, it's great. I really appreciate it. It's nice to have you on the show.
All right, I also need to take a minute. I gotta thank everyone who's been watching the show. Thank you for your feedback. You know, if you would like to appear on the show, you can contact us at methodhappenings02155 at gmail.com. You'll be able to watch replays of this program on Method Community Media Access Channel.
Check out our website methodhappenings.com
And you can now either view or listen. We also have a podcast so you can listen to the program. And you can find all of our shows on YouTube. Just go to YouTube, search for Method Happenings. Very, very easy. And if you get there, or when you get there, please like and subscribe to our channels and videos. You'll also find us on Facebook at Method Happenings.
We also have our own subreddit which you can find us at reddit.com slash a slash method happenings so for the method happening team Paul Marco Bruce James. I'm John Petrella and remember method, please stay informed. I